<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    DO NOT ALTER OR REMOVE COPYRIGHT NOTICES OR THIS HEADER.

    Copyright (c) 2013-2014 Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

    The contents of this file are subject to the terms of either the GNU
    General Public License Version 2 only ("GPL") or the Common Development
    and Distribution License("CDDL") (collectively, the "License").  You
    may not use this file except in compliance with the License.  You can
    obtain a copy of the License at
    http://glassfish.java.net/public/CDDL+GPL_1_1.html
    or packager/legal/LICENSE.txt.  See the License for the specific
    language governing permissions and limitations under the License.

    When distributing the software, include this License Header Notice in each
    file and include the License file at packager/legal/LICENSE.txt.

    GPL Classpath Exception:
    Oracle designates this particular file as subject to the "Classpath"
    exception as provided by Oracle in the GPL Version 2 section of the License
    file that accompanied this code.

    Modifications:
    If applicable, add the following below the License Header, with the fields
    enclosed by brackets [] replaced by your own identifying information:
    "Portions Copyright [year] [name of copyright owner]"

    Contributor(s):
    If you wish your version of this file to be governed by only the CDDL or
    only the GPL Version 2, indicate your decision by adding "[Contributor]
    elects to include this software in this distribution under the [CDDL or GPL
    Version 2] license."  If you don't indicate a single choice of license, a
    recipient has the option to distribute your version of this file under
    either the CDDL, the GPL Version 2 or to extend the choice of license to
    its licensees as provided above.  However, if you add GPL Version 2 code
    and therefore, elected the GPL Version 2 license, then the option applies
    only if the new code is made subject to such option by the copyright
    holder.

-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter [<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "tyrus.ent" > %ents;]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:lang="en"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
                             http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink.xsd"
         xml:id="tyrus-proprietary-config">
    <title>Tyrus proprietary configuration</title>

    <para>Following settings do have influence on Tyrus behaviour and are <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> part of WebSocket
    specification. If you are using following configurable options, your application might not be easily transferable to
    other WebSocket API implementation.</para>

    <section>
        <title>Client-side SSL configuration</title>

        <para>When accessing "wss" URLs, Tyrus client will pick up whatever keystore and truststore is actually set for current JVM instance, but
            that might not be always convenient. WebSocket API does not have this feature (yet, see <link xlink:href="https://java.net/jira/browse/WEBSOCKET_SPEC-210">WEBSOCKET_SPEC-210</link>),
            so Tyrus exposed <link xlink:href="https://grizzly.java.net/docs/2.3/apidocs/org/glassfish/grizzly/ssl/SSLEngineConfigurator.html">SSLEngineConfigurator</link> class from Grizzly which can be used for specifying all SSL parameters
            to be used with current client instance. Additionally, WebSocket API does not have anything like a client,
            only WebSocketContainer and it does not have any properties, so you need to use Tyrus specific class -
            <link xlink:href="https://tyrus.java.net/apidocs/&version;/org/glassfish/tyrus/client/ClientManager.html">ClientManager</link>.</para>

        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">final ClientManager client = ClientManager.createClient();

System.getProperties().put("javax.net.debug", "all");
System.getProperties().put(SSLContextConfigurator.KEY_STORE_FILE, "...");
System.getProperties().put(SSLContextConfigurator.TRUST_STORE_FILE, "...");
System.getProperties().put(SSLContextConfigurator.KEY_STORE_PASSWORD, "...");
System.getProperties().put(SSLContextConfigurator.TRUST_STORE_PASSWORD, "...");
final SSLContextConfigurator defaultConfig = new SSLContextConfigurator();

defaultConfig.retrieve(System.getProperties());
    // or setup SSLContextConfigurator using its API.

SSLEngineConfigurator sslEngineConfigurator =
    new SSLEngineConfigurator(defaultConfig, true, false, false);
client.getProperties().put(GrizzlyEngine.SSL_ENGINE_CONFIGURATOR,
    sslEngineConfigurator);
client.connectToServer(... , ClientEndpointConfig.Builder.create().build(),
    new URI("wss://localhost:8181/sample-echo/echo"));
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Asynchronous connectToServer methods</title>
        <para>WebSocketContainer.connectToServer(...) methods are by definition blocking - declared exceptions needs to
        be thrown after connection attempt is made and it returns Session instance, which needs to be ready for sending
        messages and invoking other methods, which require already estabilished connection.</para>
        <para>Existing connectToServer methods are fine for lots of uses, but it might cause issue when you are designing
        application with highly responsible user interface. Tyrus introduces asynchronous variants to each connectToServer
        method (prefixed with "async"), which returns Future&lt;Session&gt;. These methods do only simple check for provided
        URL and the rest is executed in separate thread. All exceptions thrown during this phase are reported as cause
        of ExecutionException thrown when calling Future&lt;Session&gt;.get().</para>
        <para>Asynchronous connect methods are declared on Tyrus implementation of WebSocketContainer called ClientManager.</para>

<programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">ClientManager client = ClientManager.createClient();
  final Future&lt;Session&gt; future = client.asyncConnectToServer(ClientEndpoint.class, URI.create("..."));
  try {
    future.get();
  } catch (...) {
}</programlisting>

        <para>ClientManager contains async alternative to each connectToServer method.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Optimized broadcast</title>
        <para>One of the typical usecases we've seen so far for WebSocket server-side endpoints is broadcasting messages
        to all connected clients, something like:</para>

<programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">@OnMessage
public void onMessage(Session session, String message) throws IOException {
  for (Session s : session.getOpenSessions()) {
    s.getBasicRemote().sendText(message);
  }
}</programlisting>

        <para>Executing this code might cause serious load increase on your application server. Tyrus provides optimized
        broadcast implementation, which takes advantage of the fact, that we are sending exactly same message to all clients,
        so dataframe can be created and serialized only once. Furthermore, Tyrus can iterate over set of opened connections
        faster than Session.getOpenSession().</para>

<programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">@OnMessage
public void onMessage(Session session, String message) {
  ((TyrusSession) session).broadcast(message);
}</programlisting>

        <para>Unfortunately, WebSocket API forbids anything else than Session in @OnMessage annotated method parameter,
        so you cannot use TyrusSession there directly and you might need to perform instanceof check.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Incoming buffer size</title>

        <para>Sevlet container buffers incoming WebSocket frames and there must be a size limit to precede OutOfMemory
        Exception and potentially DDoS attacks.</para>

        <para>Configuration property is named <code>"org.glassfish.tyrus.servlet.incoming-buffer-size"</code> and you can
        set it in web.xml (this particular snipped sets the buffer size to 17000000 bytes (~16M payload):</para>

        <programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="numbered">&lt;web-app version="2.5" xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee/web-app_2_5.xsd"&gt;

  &lt;context-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;org.glassfish.tyrus.servlet.incoming-buffer-size&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;17000000&lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/context-param&gt;
&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Default value is 4194315, which correspond to 4M plus few bytes to frame headers, so you should be able to
        receive up to 4M long message without the need to care about this property.</para>

        <para>Same issue is present on client side. There you can set this property via ClientManager:</para>

        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">ClientManager client = ClientManager.createClient();
client.getProperties().put("org.glassfish.tyrus.incomingBufferSize", 6000000); // sets the incoming buffer size to 6000000 bytes.
client.connectToServer( ... )</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Shared client container</title>

        <para>By default, WebSocket client implementation in Tyrus re-creates client runtime whenever WebSocketContainer#connectToServer
            is invoked. This approach gives us some perks like out-of-the-box isolation and relatively low thread count
            (currently we have 1 selector thread and 2 worker threads). Also it gives you the ability to stop the client
            runtime – one Session instance is tied to exactly one client runtime, so we can stop it when Session is closed.
            This seems as a good solution for most of WebSocket client use cases – you usually use java client from
            application which uses it for communicating with server side and you typically don’t need more than 10 instances
            (my personal estimate is that more than 90% applications won’t use more than 1 connection). There are several
            reasons for it – of it is just a client, it needs to preserve server resources – one WebSocket connection means
            one TCP connection and we don’t really want clients to consume more than needed. Previous statement may be
            invalidated by WebSocket multiplexing extension, but for now, it is still valid.</para>

        <para>On the other hand, WebSocket client implementations in some other containers took another (also correct)
            approach – they share client runtime for creating all client connections. That means they might not have this
            strict one session one runtime policy, they cannot really give user way how he to control system resources,
            but surely it has another advantage – it can handle much more opened connections. Thread pools are share among
            client sessions which may or may not have some unforeseen consequences, but if its implemented correctly, it
            should outperform Tyrus solution mentioned in previous paragraph in some use cases, like the one mentioned
            in <link xlink:href="https://java.net/jira/browse/TYRUS-275">TYRUS-275</link> - performance tests. Reporter
            created simple program which used WebSocket API to create clients and connect to remote endpoint and he measured
            how many clients can he create (or in other words: how many parallel client connections can be created; I guess
            that original test case is to measure possible number of concurrent clients on server side, but that does not
            really matter for this post). Tyrus implementation loose compared to some other and it was exactly because it
            did not have shared client runtime capability.</para>

        <para>How can you use this feature?</para>

<programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">ClientManager client = ClientManager.createClient();

client.getProperties().put(GrizzlyClientContainer.SHARED_CONTAINER, true);</programlisting>

        <para>You might also want to specify container idle timeout:</para>

<programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">client.getProperties().put(GrizzlyClientContainer.SHARED_CONTAINER_IDLE_TIMEOUT, 5);</programlisting>

        <para>Last but not least, you might want to specify thread pool sizes used by shared container (please use this feature only when you do know what are you doing. Grizzly by default does not limit max number of used threads, so if you do that, please make sure thread pool size fits your purpose):</para>

<programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">client.getProperties().put(GrizzlyClientSocket.SELECTOR_THREAD_POOL_CONFIG, ThreadPoolConfig.defaultConfig().setMaxPoolSize(3));
client.getProperties().put(GrizzlyClientSocket.WORKER_THREAD_POOL_CONFIG, ThreadPoolConfig.defaultConfig().setMaxPoolSize(10));</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>WebSocket Extensions</title>

        <para>Please note that Extensions support is considered to be experimental and any API can be changed anytime. Also,
        you should ask yourself at least twice whether you don't want to achieve your goal by other means - WebSocket
        Extension is very powerful and can easily break your application when not used with care or enough expertise.
        </para>

        <para>WebSocket frame used in ExtendedExtension:</para>

        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">public class Frame {

    public boolean isFin() { .. }
    public boolean isRsv1() { .. }
    public boolean isRsv2() { .. }
    public boolean isRsv3() { .. }
    public boolean isMask() { .. }
    public byte getOpcode() { .. }
    public long getPayloadLength() { .. }
    public int getMaskingKey() { .. }
    public byte[] getPayloadData() { .. }
    public boolean isControlFrame() { .. }

    public static Builder builder() { .. }
    public static Builder builder(Frame frame) { .. }

    public final static class Builder {

    public Builder() { .. }
    public Builder(Frame frame) { .. }
    public Frame build() { .. }
    public Builder fin(boolean fin) { .. }
    public Builder rsv1(boolean rsv1) { .. }
    public Builder rsv2(boolean rsv2) { .. }
    public Builder rsv3(boolean rsv3) { .. }
    public Builder mask(boolean mask) { .. }
    public Builder opcode(byte opcode) { .. }
    public Builder payloadLength(long payloadLength) { .. }
    public Builder maskingKey(int maskingKey) { .. }
    public Builder payloadData(byte[] payloadData) { .. }
}</programlisting>

        <para>Frame is immutable, so if you want to create new one, you need to create new builder, modify what you want
        and build it:</para>

        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">Frame newFrame = Frame.builder(originalFrame).rsv1(true).build();</programlisting>

        <para>Note that there is only one convenience method: isControlFrame. Other information about frame type etc needs
            to be evaluated directly from opcode, simply because there might not be enough information to get the correct
            outcome or the information itself would not be very useful. For example: opcode 0×00 means continuation frame,
            but you don’t have any chance to get the information about actual type (text or binary) without intercepting
            data from previous frames. Consider Frame class as raw representation as possible. isControlFrame() can be also
            gathered from opcode, but it is at least always deterministic and it will be used by most of extension
            implementations. It is not usual to modify control frames as it might end with half closed connections or
            unanswered ping messages.</para>

        <para>ExtendedExtension representation needs to be able to handle extension parameter negotiation and actual processing
        of incoming and outgoing frames. It also should be compatible with existing javax.websocket.Extension class, since we
        want to re-use existing registration API and be able to return new extension instance included in response
        from List&lt;Extension&gt; Session.getNegotiatedExtensions() call. Consider following:</para>

        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">public interface ExtendedExtension extends Extension {

    Frame processIncoming(ExtensionContext context, Frame frame);
    Frame processOutgoing(ExtensionContext context, Frame frame);

    List onExtensionNegotiation(ExtensionContext context, List requestedParameters);
    void onHandshakeResponse(ExtensionContext context, List responseParameters);

    void destroy(ExtensionContext context);

    interface ExtensionContext {

        Map&lt;String, Object> getProperties();
    }
}</programlisting>

        <para>ExtendedExtension is capable of processing frames and influence parameter values during the handshake.
            Extension is used on both client and server side and since the negotiation is only place where this fact
            applies, we needed to somehow differentiate these sides. On server side, only onExtensionNegotiation(..)
            method is invoked and on client side onHandshakeResponse(..). Server side method is a must, client side could
            be somehow solved by implementing ClientEndpointConfig.Configurator#afterResponse(..) or calling
            Session.getNegotiatedExtenions(), but it won’t be as easy to get this information back to extension instance
            and even if it was, it won’t be very elegant. Also, you might suggest replacing processIncoming and
            processOutgoing methods by just oneprocess(Frame) method. That is also possible, but then you might have to
            assume current direction from frame instance or somehow from ExtensionContext, which is generally not a bad
            idea, but it resulted it slightly less readable code.</para>

        <para>ExtensionContext and related lifecycle method is there because original javax.websocket.Extension is singleton
        and ExtendedExtension must obey this fact. But it does not meet some requirements we stated previously, like per
        connection parameter negotiation and of course processing itself will most likely have some connection state.
        Lifecycle of ExtensionContext is defined as follows: ExtensionContext instance is created right before onExtensionNegotiation
        (server side) or onHandshakeResponse (client side) and destroyed after destroy method invocation. Obviously, processIncoming
        or processOutgoing cannot be called before ExtensionContext is created or after is destroyed. You can think of handshake
        related methods as @OnOpenand destroy as @OnClose.</para>

        <para>For those more familiar with WebSocket protocol: process*(ExtensionContext, Frame) is always invoked with unmasked
        frame, you don’t need to care about it. On the other side, payload is as it was received from the wire, before any
            validation (UTF-8 check for text messages). This fact is particularly important when you are modifying text
            message content, you need to make sure it is properly encoded in relation to other messages, because encoding/decoding
            process is stateful – remainder after UTF-8 coding is used as input to coding process for next message. If you
            want just test this feature and save yourself some headaches, don’t modify text message content or try binary
            messages instead.</para>

        <section>
            <title>ExtendedExtension sample</title>

        <para>Let’s say we want to create extension which will encrypt and decrypt first byte of every binary message. Assume we have a key (one byte) and our symmetrical cipher will be XOR. (Just for simplicity (a XOR key XOR key) = a, so encrypt() and decrypt() functions are the same).</para>
            <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">public class CryptoExtension implements ExtendedExtension {

    @Override
    public Frame processIncoming(ExtensionContext context, Frame frame) {
         return lameCrypt(context, frame);
    }

    @Override
    public Frame processOutgoing(ExtensionContext context, Frame frame) {
        return lameCrypt(context, frame);
    }

    private Frame lameCrypt(ExtensionContext context, Frame frame) {
        if(!frame.isControlFrame() &amp;&amp; (frame.getOpcode() == 0x02)) {
            final byte[] payloadData = frame.getPayloadData();
            payloadData[0] ^= (Byte)(context.getProperties().get("key"));

            return Frame.builder(frame).payloadData(payloadData).build();
        } else {
            return frame;
        }
    }

    @Override
    public List onExtensionNegotiation(ExtensionContext context,
                                       List requestedParameters) {
        init(context);
        // no params.
        return null;
    }

    @Override
    public void onHandshakeResponse(ExtensionContext context,
    List responseParameters) {
        init(context);
    }

    private void init(ExtensionContext context) {
        context.getProperties().put("key", (byte)0x55);
    }

    @Override
    public void destroy(ExtensionContext context) {
        context.getProperties().clear();
    }

    @Override
    public String getName() {
        return "lame-crypto-extension";
    }

    @Override
    public List getParameters() {
        // no params.
        return null;
    }
}</programlisting>

        <para>You can see that ExtendedExtension is slightly more complicated that original Extension so the implementation
            has to be also not as straightforward.. on the other hand, it does something. Sample code above shows possible
            simplification mentioned earlier (one process method will be enough), but please take this as just sample
            implementation. Real world case is usually more complicated.</para>

        <para>Now when we have our CryptoExtension implemented, we want to use it. There is nothing new compared to standard
            WebSocket Java API, feel free to skip this part if you are already familiar with it. Only programmatic version
            will be demonstrated. It is possible to do it for annotated version as well, but it is little bit more complicated
            on the server side and I want to keep the code as compact as possible.</para>

        <para>Client registration</para>

            <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">ArrayList extensions = new ArrayList();
extensions.add(new CryptoExtension());

final ClientEndpointConfig clientConfiguration =
    ClientEndpointConfig.Builder.create()
    .extensions(extensions).build();

WebSocketContainer client = ContainerProvider.getWebSocketContainer();
final Session session = client.connectToServer(new Endpoint() {
    @Override
    public void onOpen(Session session, EndpointConfig config) {
        // ...
    }
}, clientConfiguration, URI.create(/* ... */));</programlisting>

       <para>Server registration:</para>

       <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">public class CryptoExtensionApplicationConfig implements ServerApplicationConfig {

    @Override
    public Set getEndpointConfigs(Set&lt;Class&lt;? extends Endpoint>> endpointClasses) {
        Set endpointConfigs = new HashSet();
        endpointConfigs.add(
            ServerEndpointConfig.Builder.create(EchoEndpoint.class, "/echo")
            .extensions(Arrays.asList(new CryptoExtension())).build()
        );
        return endpointConfigs;
    }

    @Override
    public Set&lt;Class&lt;?>> getAnnotatedEndpointClasses(Set&lt;Class&lt;?>> scanned) {
        // all scanned endpoints will be used.
        return scanned;
    }
}

public class EchoEndpoint extends Endpoint {
    @Override
    public void onOpen(Session session, EndpointConfig config) {
        // ...
    }
}</programlisting>

            <para>CryptoExtensionApplicationConfig will be found by servlets scanning mechanism and automatically used for
                application configuration, no need to add anything (or even have) web.xml.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Per Message Deflate Extension</title>

            <para>The original goal of whole extension support was to implement Permessage extension as defined in
                draft-ietf-hybi-permessage-compression-15 and we were able to achieve that goal. Well, not completely, current
                implementation ignores parameters. But it seems like it does not matter much, it was tested with Chrome and it
                works fine. Also it passes newest version of Autobahn test suite, which includes tests for this extension.</para>

            <para>see PerMessageDeflateExtension.java (compatible with draft-ietf-hybi-permessage-compression-15, autobahn test suite) and
                XWebKitDeflateExtension.java (compatible with Chrome and Firefox – same as previous, just different extension name)
                </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Client reconnect</title>

        <para>If you need semi-persistent client connection, you can always implement some reconnect logic by yourself,
        but Tyrus Client offers useful feature which should be much easier to use. See short sample code:</para>

        <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">ClientManager client = ClientManager.createClient();
ClientManager.ReconnectHandler reconnectHandler = new ClientManager.ReconnectHandler() {

  private int counter = 0;

  @Override
  public boolean onDisconnect(CloseReason closeReason) {
    counter++;
    if (counter &lt;= 3) {
      System.out.println("### Reconnecting... (reconnect count: " + counter + ")");
      return true;
    } else {
      return false;
    }
  }

  @Override
  public boolean onConnectFailure(Exception exception) {
    counter++;
    if (counter &lt;= 3) {
      System.out.println("### Reconnecting... (reconnect count: " + counter + ") " + exception.getMessage());

      // Thread.sleep(...) or something other "sleep-like" expression can be put here - you might want
      // to do it here to avoid potential DDoS when you don't limit number of reconnects.
      return true;
    } else {
      return false;
    }
  }
};

client.getProperties().put(ClientManager.RECONNECT_HANDLER, reconnectHandler);

client.connectToServer(...)</programlisting>

        <para>As you can see, ReconnectHandler contains two methods, onDisconnect and onConnectFailure. First will be executed
        whenever @OnClose annotated method (or Endpoint.onClose(..)) is executed on client side - this should happen when
        established connection is lost for any reason. You can find the reason in methods parameter. Other one, called
        onConnectFailure is invoked when client fails to connect to remote endpoint, for example due to temporary network
        issue or current high server load.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>JDK 7 client</title>
        <para>
            As has been said in previous chapters both Tyrus client and server were implemented on top of Grizzly NIO framework.
            This still remains true, but an alternative Tyrus Websocket client implementation based on Java 7 Asynchronous Channel
            API has been available since version 1.6. There are two options how to switch between client implementations.
            If you do not mind using Tyrus specific API, the most straightforward way is to use:
            <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">
                final ClientManager client = ClientManager.createClient(JdkClientContainer.class.getName());
            </programlisting>
            You just have to make sure that the dependency on JDK client is included in your project:
            <programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="unnumbered">
                &lt;dependency&gt;
                    &lt;groupId&gt;org.glassfish.tyrus&lt;/groupId&gt;
                    &lt;artifactId&gt;tyrus-container-jdk-client&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                    &lt;version&gt;&version;&lt;/version&gt;
                &lt;/dependency&gt;
            </programlisting>
            Grizzly client is the default option, so creating a client without any parameters will result in Grizzly client being used.
        </para>
        <para>
            There is also an option how to use JDK client with the standard Websocket API.
            <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">
                final WebSocketContainer client = ContainerProvider.getWebSocketContainer();
            </programlisting>
            The code listed above will scan class path for Websocket client implementations. A slight problem with this
            approach is that if there is more than one client on the classpath, the first one discovered will be used.
            Therefore if you intend to use JDK client with the standard API, you have to make sure that there is not
            a Grizzly client on the classpath as it might be used instead.
        </para>
        <para>
            The main reason why JDK client has been implemented is that it does not have any extra dependencies
            except JDK 7 and of course some other Tyrus modules, which makes it considerable more lightweight compared
            to Tyrus Grizzly client, which requires 1.4 MB of dependencies.
        </para>
        <para>
            It is also important to note that the JDK client has been implemented in a way similar to Grizzly client
            shared container option, which means that there is one thread pool shared among all clients. Unlike in the
            case of Grizzly client there are no configuration options available for JDK client and JDK client also
            does not support SSL and proxy traversing.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>